<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Corporal vvorship discuss'd and defended in a sermon preached at the visitation April 21, 1670, in Saviour's-Church Southwark, and published to prevent farther calumny / by W.B.</title>
            <author>Basset, William, 1644-1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26751</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1051</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37086</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16206446</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16206446</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105079</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26751)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105079)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1087:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Corporal vvorship discuss'd and defended in a sermon preached at the visitation April 21, 1670, in Saviour's-Church Southwark, and published to prevent farther calumny / by W.B.</title>
                  <author>Basset, William, 1644-1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 30, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Basset ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Christian union --  Anglican Communion.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105079:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Corporal Worſhip Diſcuſs'd and Defended: IN A SERMON Preached at the VISITATION <hi>April</hi> 21. 1670. In <hi>Saviours</hi>-Church <hi>Southwark.</hi> And Publiſhed to prevent farther Calumny.</p>
            <p>By <hi>W. B.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Baſſet,</hi> at the <hi>George</hi> near <hi>Cliffords-Inne</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> 1670.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:105079:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105079:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipful Sir <hi>Mondeford Bramston</hi> Knight; Dr. of Laws; and one of the Maſters of his Majeſties High Court of Chancery; and Chancellour of the Right Reverend Father in God <hi>George</hi> by Divine Permiſſion Lord Biſhop of <hi>Winton,</hi> my Dioceſan.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Worſhipful,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>COnſciouſneſs of my own weakneſs ſufficiently deters me from publick cenſure: therefore I ſhould not have entertain'd one thought of appearing abroad, had not this diſcourſe been made both a Chimney, and (as I may ſpeak) a Pulpit-talk, amongſt the froward Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of our Church: yet, had they any thing of truth, and modeſty, in their reflections, I ſhould have layn un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concern'd beneath them: but as it is their practice to load whatever makes againſt them (to ſpeak modeſtly) with all the aggravations it is capable of receiving; ſo it is the peoples pleaſure to imbrace whatever they ſay as <hi>Folia Sibyllae,</hi> articles of faith, or undoubted maxims of truth: be pleas'd to take one inſtance, I have heard ſeveral particular perſons affirm (I am loth to ſay one of their Preachers too, who pretended he had read, and underſtood the book) that the Author of the <hi>Eccleſ. Pol.</hi> declares it more excuſable for any man to be guilty of all manner of debauchery, than to go to a private Meeting; and though I knew it was ſo grand an abuſe of
<pb facs="tcp:105079:3"/>that Ingenious Author, yet could by no means drive them from that perſwaſion, ſome of their Leaders had brought them to: and if they had the confidence to abuſe that piece, that was offered to the view of any, that would give themſelves the trouble of reading; how much more will they abuſe my Notes, if not ſuffered to ſpeak for themſelves! Theſe conſiderations put me upon ſome inlargements in tranſcribing the firſt Copy, a task You was pleaſed to lay upon me: but ſince your commands of making it publick have brought my wavering thoughts to a fixed reſolution: and ſince it is abroad, I wiſh them more candour, and ingenuity in the reading, than ſome had in the hearing of it: ſhall they think fit to oppoſe, I am ready (as much as in me lyes) to ſtrengthen thoſe aſſertions, which too much haſt hath hudled over: but as you was pleaſed to call this piece to skirmiſh from the Pulpit; and ſince to face its Enemies in the open Field; I leave it under your Conduct, and Protection; wiſhing your Authority may be both its Incouragement, and alſo a Bulwark to ſecure our Church againſt the aſſaults of her peeviſh Enemies: ſo having fought for Religion in this Church, which they have made Militant more than in a figure, you may be a Member of that, which is Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant, is the Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Humble Oratour <hi>W. B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105079:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Epiſt.</hi> Cor. <hi>6.19, 20.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>—Ye are not your own;</p>
                  <p>For ye are bought with a price; therefore glorifie God in your body, and your ſpirit, which are Gods.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>An being a rational Creature, we ſhould deal with him by reaſon; not endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to affright him into the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of a Deity, or the cloſer imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Virtue and Religion, by ſome thundring ſpeeches, which have (it may be) neither ſufficient ground to ſtand on, nor are ſtrengthen'd with any conſiderable arguments; which is a folly, that would certainly be not only decry'd, but eaſily amended too; if (in this) all would frame their diſcourſes by the Apoſtles pattern, who layes down ſuch arguments, that the duty he preſſes to, doth flow as a neceſſary conſequence from them: for diſſwading the <hi>Corinthians</hi> from fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he ſhews they belong to God by dedication and redemption; and conſequently by that double tye,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:105079:4"/>are oblig'd to all manner of virtue, and religious wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: For,</p>
            <q>
               <p>Know ye not that your body is the Temple of the Holy Ghoſt, and</p>
               <p>Ye are not your own;</p>
               <p>For ye are bought with a price; therefore glorifie God in your body, and your ſpirit.</p>
            </q>
            <p>The Text is a perfect Enthymeme, or, if you will, an imperfect Syllogiſme; with an argument inſerted between the propoſition, and concluſion.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A propoſition: <hi>Ye are not your own.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. An argument to prove it: <hi>For ye are bought with a price.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. A concluſion from that propoſition, which is uſher'd in with the Illative <hi>[therefore]</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore glorifie God in your body, and ſpirit, which are Gods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The meaning of the propoſition is clear; <hi>Ye are not your own,</hi> i. e. not <hi>proprii juris,</hi> to live as you pleaſe your ſelves: for it is contrary to the law of reaſon, as well as the expreſs law of the land, that any man ſhould imploy that, which is, <hi>alienum,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to another, as he thinks fit himſelf.</p>
            <p>But leſt the propoſition ſhould be deny'd, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle brings an argument to prove it;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ye are bought with a price;</hi> and therefore belong to him that purchas'd you.</p>
            <p>But certainly there is another way, at leaſt in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of time, before that of redemption or dedication, by which we belong to God: and that is Creation.</p>
            <p>He made, he redeem'd us, therefore we are not our own.</p>
            <p>Seeing our duty of glorifying God will follow more ſtrongly from both, I ſhall diſcourſe on each.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:105079:4"/>
            <p> That we belong to God by creation is evident, for man, and all the world, muſt</p>
            <p>Have been from Eternity,</p>
            <p>Or be made by chance,</p>
            <p>Or be the makers of themſelves,</p>
            <p>Or elſe be made by another, which can be none but God, to whom they belong.</p>
            <p>No other way, ſurely, can be imagin'd, how things could poſſibly come to an actual exiſtence: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the three firſt being evidently falſe, the laſt muſt needs be true, that we belong to God by creation; and therefore are not our own.</p>
            <p>Had the world been from Eternity,<note place="margin">Unleſs from Scripture.</note> what is the reaſon that we have no certain know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of any thing done before a few of the laſt Generations; nor any monuments of Antiquity, whoſe beginning is not either known, or ſhrewdly gueſt at? If we come to the <hi>Pyramids</hi> in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> they were thought by <hi>Joſephus</hi> to have been built by the <hi>Jews</hi> during their bondage there; and by others more probably ſince: whereas—</p>
            <p>It is but of late years, ſince many parts of the world were diſcover'd; and no longer ſince, than in the time of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, that little which was known, was ſo poorly fortified, and thinly inhabited by unskilful and timerous people, that he ſoon made himſelf Maſter of it all.</p>
            <p>Many ingenious Arts are but of late invention; and <hi>Seneca</hi> tells us it was not in his time one thouſand years ſince ingenuity and learning began to flouriſh in the world: therefore if any ſavour this opinion, they muſt have very high thoughts of this, and ſome few of the laſt Generations, and but little or no charity at all for millions before them; in leaving them like
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105079:5"/>Bruits without underſtanding, and be beholding to a few of the laſt for whatever is worthy of notice.</p>
            <p>Hence the world ſeems but of late crept out of her infancy, not yet aſcended to the Meridian of inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity and learning: whence we may as rationally conclude, that it is not of ſo long a ſtanding, as that a youth by his looks, and parts, hath not attain'd the age and experience of a full-grown man.</p>
            <p>The Heathens did generally believe that all things had a beginning: and though ſome flie to <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> as the great Patron of the worlds Eternity; yet, whatever arguments he might lay down to prove it, <hi>Barlow</hi> in his Metaphyſical Exercitations, denyes him to have been conſtantly, if ever purely of this mind: by reaſon (particularly) of his ſpeaking of an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a being from whence all other beings flow: but if this ſeems not prevalent enough, the world is compos'd of parts, and the parts muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity be before whole, in order both of time and nature; but was the world Eternal, either the whole muſt have been as ſoon as the parts, or elſe the parts muſt have been before Eternity it ſelf: neither of which reaſon can allow.</p>
            <p>It is as evident too, that things could never be made by chance, or the fortuitous union of ſome ſtragling attomes, as <hi>Epicurus</hi> ſaith: for though matter, and motion, may do ſomething, yet 'tis impoſſible they ſhould ever produce a world ſo admirably ſeated, and fitted for the entertainment of ſo many creatures; and then furniſh it too with ſuch variety of beings, which are all (in a manner) neceſſary; and ſeem not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intended for ſome end, but are ſo exactly fitted for the ſeveral ends they ſeem to be made for: all the wit in the world can never contrive how things
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105079:5"/>ſhould be better; neither the whole, nor any part, wants any thing neceſſary, nor hath any thing ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous: the Sun, Moon, and other Stars, for ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſand years together, are ſo conſtant and regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar in their motions, that day and night, Winter and Summer, are alwayes exactly at their wonted ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; all which (with much more, that might be nam'd) can never be the work of meer matter, and a fortuitous motion.</p>
            <p>It is alſo as apparently contrary to reaſon, that man, or any thing elſe, ſhould make it ſelf: for the cauſe muſt act before the effect be produced: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if man be the maker of himſelf, he muſt be both the <hi>cauſa,</hi> and the <hi>cauſatum,</hi> and conſequently muſt act in order to his own being: and hence it will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that he muſt have a being before he is made, elſe he could not act in order to his own being; for acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on neceſſarily pre-ſuppoſes being: and ſo he muſt be, and not be at the ſame inſtant; which is ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to reaſon, that we may ſafely conclude we were all made by another, which can be none but God.</p>
            <p>He made us, and not we our ſelves; we are the work of his hands, and the ſheep of his paſture: in the beginning God made Heaven, and Earth, and whatever is contain'd in either, himſelf only except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: and that, which <hi>Moſes</hi> calls the void and form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs earth, was the <hi>materia prima,</hi> out of which all earthly beings were produc'd; neither was this any Eternal matter, but was created by him, and made fit for the reception of any manner of forms, as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratory (if I may ſo ſpeak) to the great work of Creation: hence, though things were made of pre-exiſting, yet not of co-exiſting matter: and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105079:6"/>there never was any thing, but what lies un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the notion of a Creature: and therefore we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to him by Creation,</p>
            <q>And are not our own.</q>
            <p>But the expreſs argument the Apoſtle uſes to prove the propoſition is Redemption.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Ye are not your own;</p>
               <p>For ye are bought with a price.</p>
            </q>
            <p>This ſuppoſes man's fall by ſin; for unleſs he had revolted from his Creator, there had been no need of Redemption; for none buy that, which is their own: and as it ſuppoſes mans ſin, and folly, ſo it proclaims Gods goodneſs, and mercy, in not leaving him to periſh in his own devices; but in laying help upon one, that is Mighty, and able to reſcue us from the paw of the Lyon: For</p>
            <q>We are bought with a price.</q>
            <p>As Juſtice could be ſatisfied with no price of leſs than an infinite value; ſo we are bought not with corruptible things, as gold, and ſilver, but with the precious bloud of the Son of God: though it be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible there ſhould be in God any <hi>potentia paſſiva;</hi> yet there being ſo near an union between the Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Humanity of Chriſt, that what was done too, or ſuffered by one, was attributed to the other, we are truly ſaid to be redeem'd by the bloud of the Son of God: this is the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or price in the Text.</p>
            <q>Ye are bought with a price.</q>
            <p>Now we cannot in reaſon doubt, but that we are bought, the price already pay'd, and that by him too, whom we own to be the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> having ſo many things, that may ſerve as very ſtrong preparatories to bring us to this belief; and others, that do more clearly evince it.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:105079:6"/>
            <p> Among the preparatories I might reckon ſome of the Propheſies both of <hi>Sybilla Cumaea,</hi> and <hi>Sybilla Ery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thraea;</hi> and alſo the ceaſing of Oracles, mention'd by <hi>Plutarch,</hi> though by his ſtrange ſancies in that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, he plainly ſhews, he knew not the reaſon of it; which we muſt fetch from the Prophet, not the Philoſopher: as likewiſe the confeſſion of the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves, and ſome of the Heathen, as <hi>Cornel. Taci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> in particular, <hi>lib.</hi> 15. <hi>Annalium. par.</hi> 44. who own that there was ſuch a perſon as Chriſt, and that he ſuffer'd death under <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> which is agreeable with one of the Articles of our Faith: and ſhould we from hence caſt an eye upon the world, which lay groaning under the bondage of ſin, ſome of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then being puzzled, and non-pluſt, in conceiving how divine juſtice ſhould be ſatisfied; and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles alſo telling us that we were without ſtrength, ſpoyl'd of all power of doing any thing in order to our own recovery, we ſhall be much help'd toward this belief, that</p>
            <q>VVe are bought with a price.</q>
            <p>But there are other things, that do more clearly evince it, as</p>
            <p>Types under the Law, both perſons, and things, which were ſhadows of things to come, and like ſo many fingers, point out him to be the <hi>Meſſias;</hi> and all the Propheſies, like ſo many lines, do meet in him, as in their proper center.</p>
            <p>Then his Birth was ſet off with a train of wonders, as an extraordinary Star, ſuppoſed by ſome to be hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at in <hi>Balaam</hi>'s Propheſie; and a Quire of Angels ſinging, <hi>To us a Child is born, to us a Son is given.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next, behold his works, which being real miracles, muſt have been wrought by a ſupernatural power;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105079:7"/>as diſpoſſeſsing of Devils, raiſing the dead <hi>&amp;c.</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by a word, which he wrought both to prove his Divinity, and alſo the end of his coming to be the Redemption of the world.</p>
            <p>His Death likewiſe was not only follow'd by a praternatural Eclipſe, cleaving of Rocks, opening of Graves, and rending the Vale; which made the <hi>Centurion</hi> ſay, <hi>Truly this was the Son of God.:</hi> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in all points agreed with the Propheſies in the Old, and his own words in the New Teſtament: after which, having roſe again according to the Scripiure, he appear'd to above five hundred at once; and having commanded his Apoſtles to teach, and baptize all Nations, he fitted thoſe illiterate men for ſo great a task, by extraordinary gifts of the Holy Ghoſt, by which they ſpake in ſo many tongues, as wrought admiration in all the Proſelytes that heard them: all which, both proves his Divinity, and ſhews he came to</p>
            <q>Buy us with a price.</q>
            <p>Now God having ſuch an abſolute Soveraignty over, right to, and propriety in us, as he is our Creator and Redeemer: the concluſion very ſtrongly follows:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore glorifie God in your body, and ſpirit, which are Gods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As man is compounded of matter, and form, ſo God commands us to glorifie him in both: <hi>glorifie God in your body, and ſpirit:</hi> the Spirit <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is the ſame with the Soul <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>The meaning of which words we may take thus; <hi>Glorifie,</hi> i. e. declare the divine perfections, and excellencies of God; which is done ſeveral wayes.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:105079:7"/>
            <p> By intention of the Soul in all the duties,<note place="margin">In Spirit, and Body.</note> or exerciſes of religious worſhip.</p>
            <p>By innocence, and purity of life, which is oppoſed to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> fornication.</p>
            <p>And alſo by decent geſtures, reverent behaviour, and corporal adoration in all places, and times of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine worſhip.</p>
            <p>Without intention of the Soul, you give God but the husk and ſhadow.</p>
            <p>Without ſuch reverence and adoration, you offer him but an imperfect ſervice: <hi>Therefore thoſe which God hath joyned together, let no man put a ſunder:</hi> but</p>
            <q>Glorifie him in your body, and ſpirit, which are his.</q>
            <p>In all the ſeveral factions, and parties amongſt us, there is ſcarce a man, that will not grant it a duty to glorifie God in the Spirit; and indeed they ſeparate from us meerly upon pretence of ſetting up a more pure and ſpiritual worſhip: and when we ſpeak of ſuch reverence and adoration, they think to ſtop our mouths with that Text, <hi>John</hi> 4.24. <hi>The true worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers ſhall worſhip in ſpirit and in truth:</hi> if we take the words as much in their ſenſe as we can, they do not exclude ſuch reverence and adoration; for this is in, and flows from a ſpiritual devotion: they may as well hold that he, that prays, or ſings, ſhould not ſpeak at all, becauſe the Apoſtle ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15. <hi>That he will do both in the ſpirit, and in the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing:</hi> but though this be a Text very illy, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdly applyed to their purpoſe, as having quite ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſign; for by this Chriſt ſhews the <hi>Samaritan</hi> woman, that the time is coming, when the true worſhippers ſhall worſhip, not with types, and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows of things to come, as in the Old Teſtament, but according to the verity of things exhibited in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105079:8"/>Chriſt: yet their quoting and wreſting of this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, doth plainly ſhew, that as on the one hand, they ſeem very zealous of glorifying God in their ſpirits; ſo, on the other, they are very averſe from, and reſolute againſt glorifying him in their bodies: I need not therefore inſiſt on the chiefer part, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing own'd, not only by our Church, but by all thoſe, who would make themſelves our Adverſaries too; conſider them under what notion or terms you pleaſe: and will therefore diſcourſe on glorifying God in our bodies, by decent geſtures, reverent behaviour, and corporal adoration.</p>
            <p>They cannot deny but that God made the body, as well as the ſoul; for elſe the body can be no crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or part of the creation.</p>
            <p>Neither can they deny but that God redeem'd both, for elſe the body can never partake of future happineſs, ſeeing without redemption there is no ſalvation: and conſequently if there be any glorified ſouls, they ſhall never be re-united to their bodies after the reſurrection, but remain in perpetual ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: and if ſo, what reaſon can they give for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying God that glory, and worſhip, which is due from one; ſeeing he hath the ſame right and title to both!</p>
            <p>They likewiſe, as well as we, expect, and hope, that their bodies ſhould be ſaved in the day of our Lord Jeſus: and we know that a reward doth ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily preſuppoſe a duty: upon what ground then can they hope that God ſhould glorifie their bodies hereafter, if they refuſe to glorifie him in their bodies here?</p>
            <p>Should they ſay, they do it ſufficiently by keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their bodies, as much as in them lyes, from
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105079:8"/>being inſtruments of ſin; as fornication, or the like.</p>
            <p>I think, I may anſwer, this is but a negative de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, which alone cannot denominate any man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, for — <hi>ex puris negativis nihil concluditur:</hi> as there is a poſitive happineſs for body, and ſoul; ſo there are poſitive commands and conſequently poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive duties to be perform'd by each.</p>
            <p>But becauſe they may inſtance in ſome poſitive du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, they perform with their bodies, as well as the ſoul; ſuch as be ſinging, praying, and preaching.</p>
            <p>I therefore add,</p>
            <p>As God hath by Creation, Redemption, Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, Promiſes, and the like, lay'd all the obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions upon us, that can be, to be religious; ſo we ſhould uſe all means, or wayes poſſibly of glorifying him; and if ſuch reverence, and adoration, be not one, I hardly know what is: for as the ſoul is the chiefer part of man, but yet is no man, till it be joyn'd with the body; ſo the internal devotion of the ſoul is the chiefer part of religious worſhip; but yet this worſhip is imperfect, till it be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with the reverence and adoration of the body, and that exerciſe of the body before mention'd, in ſinging, praying, and preaching, if there be any other ſuch ſmall things, do make up but a very lame ſervice; whilſt reverent geſtures, and corporal adoration is wanting: they throw in their <hi>Annis,</hi> and <hi>Cummin,</hi> whilſt the greater matters of the body are ſtill neglected.</p>
            <p>Let me urge for adoration; which being proved, decent geſtures, and reverent behaviour will be proved too: as <hi>omne majus continet minus:</hi> or as they are ſmaller parts of ſuch adoration.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:105079:9"/>
            <p> God did forbid the Jews, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.5. <hi>to bow down to any graven Image:</hi> which corporal adoration is a part of divine worſhip, elſe it would not be forbid to be done to Idols; whence it appears that this bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the head, or body, is unlawful only when termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated to wrong objects, as Images; and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is lawful, and neceſſary too, when terminated to the right, as the true God; and therefore this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of worſhip muſt needs be (at leaſt) lawful, nay neceſſary, if done to the true God only; or out of reverence to him, toward the place where he is moſt eſpecially preſent: and accordingly we find that this was practis'd by the <hi>Jews</hi> without any imputation of ſin: as I ſhall ſhew anon.</p>
            <p>Neither can they ſay, that this was aboliſhed by Chriſt.</p>
            <p>For the morality of this command doth ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhew it's perpetuity: as it is a perpetual prohibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Thou ſhalt not bow down to any graven Image;</hi> ſo it is a perpetual obligation, <hi>Thou ſhalt bow down to the true God:</hi> for ſo long as corporal adoration of Images remains forbidden, ſo long corporal adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the true God is a part of divine worſhip, and ſo remains our duty: and, I hope, you will be unwilling enough to take away this command, when you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the conſequences of it; for the command being taken away, that, which is forbid by it, will become lawful, and ſo we may worſhip Images.</p>
            <p>They cannot poſſibly wind off this by ſaying they do it ſufficiently in kneeling to him in prayer; for this is but a part of corporal adoration: but (to come ſo far to them) ſhould they anſwer thus, they muſt allow kneeling to be a duty: and if ſo, why (I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) ſhould it be a duty in their private families, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:105079:9"/>none in the publick Congregation: where their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice ſhews, that they think it enough, forſooth, to ſit upon their tails, with their hats (it may be) half on their heads.</p>
            <p>We read of ſuch manner of adoration, before there was any law in the world, beſide that of nature, and ſpecial revelation: for <hi>Abraham</hi> bowed himſelf before God, and the Gentiles in all parts of the world did the ſame to thoſe things, which they own'd as Gods; which ſhews that this is natural, and conſequently perpetually obliging: for as reaſon, and conſcience, tells us that there is a God, ſo they oblige us to worſhip that God with all reverence, and adoration imaginable: and as many Authors build an argument upon the former to prove the exiſtence of a Deity; ſo we may build as ſtrong an argument on the latter to prove corporal adoration: for the law of nature binds as ſtrong in the one, as in the other: and though in that firſt age of the world, God appeared by created Angels, or otherwiſe, in viſible ſhapes; which ſome (poſſibly) may think requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſuch ſpecial reverence, and adoration; yet we have his promiſe, <hi>that when two, or three, are gathered together in his name, he will be in the midst of them:</hi> and the Apoſtle likewiſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.10. tells us that Angels are preſent in places, and times of divine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and therefore we are as much oblig'd to pay this reverence, and adoration, as if God by thoſe Angels, or any otherwiſe, was viſibly amongſt us; being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly aſſured both by his promiſe, and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle too, that he is preſent (eſpecially) in conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted places, at ſuch times of worſhip.</p>
            <p>As this is a part of worſhip, and therefore neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in it ſelf, ſo it is neceſſary, not only as it ſpeaks
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105079:10"/>the internal devotion of the ſoul; for how can I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare this, or any awe, or fear of God, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence and adoration: words are not ſufficient, for many will hardly believe words, unleſs they ſee ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able actions: nor yet is a ſober, virtuous life enough, for ſome of the Heathen were eminent for moral vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and yet were very ſlack, or no worſhippers of any God at all: and we find it no great rarity to ſee virtue ſhine very bright in ſome, whom the <hi>Presbite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> themſelves confidently brand for carnal men: but alſo as it heightens that internal devotion, for a being bare, ſtanding, kneeling, bowing, and the like, muſt needs affect man with thoughts of his own vileneſs, and the awefulneſs of that Majeſty he is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; like <hi>Abraham,</hi> who falling on his face ſaid, <hi>I am but dust, and aſhes:</hi> it being natural to man to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend from things ſenſible to thoſe, that are purely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible: and certainly 'tis a part of prudence, as well as duty, to uſe all means poſſible of raiſing our devotion as high as we can.</p>
            <p>That men may not ſtill think this a late invention of our Church, or an old error of <hi>Rome,</hi> from whence they fancy we have whatever is decent, and comely, they may ſee the Apoſtle himſelf very preſſing to this purpoſe; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. where he both tells the men their duty in Churches, and likewiſe reproves the women's irreverence there: <hi>verſe</hi> 4, 5. <hi>Every man praying, or propheſying, with his head covered, diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours his head; and every woman, that prays, or prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, with her head uncovered, diſhonours her head:</hi> where by propheſying we muſt underſtand ſinging, which hath commonly that term put upon it, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Old Teſtament, but amongſt the Heathen too, who ſometimes call'd their Poets Prophets, as
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105079:10"/>the learned <hi>Mede</hi> doth very largely ſhew: for wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men were not ſuffered to ſpeak in the Church in a way of teaching: now the fault was the ſame in the women to be uncovered, or the men to be covered: and the argument he uſes to diſſwade them from thoſe undecent cuſtoms to this more reverent behaviour, is, becauſe of the Angels, <hi>verſe</hi> 10. they being preſent in places, and times of divine worſhip, we ought to behave our ſelves reverently; and as they are there all the time, ſo ſhould we be reverent all the time too: which is very poorly practis'd by thoſe, who are willing to be ſo far reverent, as to be uncover'd at the ſinging Pſalmes, which are almoſt ſpoyl'd in <hi>Hopkin</hi>'s Poetry; or, as one ſpeaks, in Meeter, and good meaning; but are unwilling to be uncovered at the reading Pſalms, or any other parts of Scripture, which they have purely from the original: which being cover'd, and uncover'd, we may extend to other parts of external reverence, and corporal ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: for it is impoſſible there ſhould be too much of decency, reverence, and adoration, where God is preſent by his Angels: as <hi>Jacob</hi> having ſeen them aſcending, and deſcending in a viſion, ſaid, when he wak'd, <hi>how dreadful is this place, it is no other than the houſe of God!</hi> ſo methinks their preſence in ſuch places ſhould awe us into the greateſt of internal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, and external reverence too; for how dreadful are ſuch places, becauſe of the Angels!</p>
            <p>It is very ſtrongly held by ſome, the fore-quoted Author in particular; that ſome, or other of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels are conſtantly in conſecrated places, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when ever we enter into, or paſs through thoſe places, we ought to ſhew ſomething of reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, whether it be at time of Service, or no,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105079:11"/>and that upon the ſame reaſon, becauſe of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe we cannot undoubtedly prove this ſo, yet, I am confident, we can bring far better arguments to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the undenyable proof of it, than can poſſibly be brought againſt it; therefore this muſt needs be the ſafer way: and certainly except men out of a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of contradiction, were grown fool-hardy in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, they would never run the hazard of irreverence, and contempt of holy things, and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: but in time of ſervice it is undenyable from the Apoſtle's words, that we ought to be reverent, becauſe of the Angels.</p>
            <p>I may urge farther,</p>
            <p>Churches ought not to be prophan'd, or put to common uſes, as the Apoſtle ſhews by an alluſion in the next preceeding verſe; <hi>viz. know ye not that your bodies are the Temples of the Holy Ghoſt?</hi> which he urges as an argument to diſſwade them from pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting themſelves by fornication: for as Temples are dedicated to God, and upon that very account ought to be ſet apart from all common uſes, which are a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanation of them: ſo man being dedicated to God, by his baptiſmal vow, beſide voluntary ingagements he layes upon himſelf after he comes to years of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, which I ſuppoſe at one time, or other, to be done by all; ought likewiſe upon that account, as well as others, to keep himſelf from pollution by ſin: by this alluſion it is undenyably evident, that Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ought to be kept holy; but if any ſhould ſay the Apoſtle alludes here chiefly, if not only, to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Temple, the non-prophanation of which was a part of the ceremonial law, which is abrogated by Chriſt: I think it very improbable he ſhould allude to that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105079:11"/>place, which, with all the ceremonies belonging to it, were very imperfectly known to theſe <hi>Corinthians;</hi> but to put you quite out of doubt, you may ſee the ſame Apoſtle ſpeak more plainly, and expreſly of Chriſtian Churches, there being ſome even in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> time, in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.22. where he reproves the <hi>Corinthians</hi> for feaſting in thoſe ſacred places, <hi>Have ye not houſes to eat and drink in? Or deſpiſe you the Church of God?</hi> The Church, though it be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which moſt commonly ſignifies the people, yet we muſt here underſtand it of the place; it being oppos'd to houſe: <hi>Have ye not houſes to eat and drink in? Or deſpiſe ye the Church of God?</hi> Which expoſition is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry agreeable to Mr. <hi>Vine</hi>'s ſenſe on the place, about the beginning of his ſecond Chapter of his Treatiſe on the Sacrament: whom I name, becauſe his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority is very prevalent with thoſe, I have to do with: which manifeſtly ſhews, that a putting Churches to any common uſe, is a prophaning, or deſpiſing of them; even according to Scripture, as well as the Canon: from whence I argue:</p>
            <p>If we ought not to put thoſe places to common uſes, certainly we ought not to come into them with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon geſtures, and behaviour: for I can ſee very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, if any difference at all, between one, and the other: becauſe the ſin lyes in making conſecrated, or ſeparated places, common with others; which is done by common geſtures, rude behaviour, and want of corporal adoration, as well as by eating, and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>Though not many years ſince, Churches were turn'd to Stables; and even now a prophanation of all things Sacred is made a piece of Religion, and accounted a charectiriſtical letter to diſtinguiſh the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105079:12"/>good people (as they call themſelves) from others; yet if eating, and drinking, which is good, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary in it ſelf, was unlawful only upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, becauſe done in that place, to be ſure rude, and unſeemly behaviour is unlawful too upon the ſame account; becauſe a needleſs doing any thing, that is common in the Church of God, is a deſpiſing it, it being ſet a part for holy uſes.</p>
            <p>Queſtionleſs holineſs is moſt fit for holy places; the greateſt reverence, and adoration, beſt becomes the houſe of the great God.</p>
            <p>But I am confident I might have ſpared all this pains, If I could perſwade theſe men to be as zealous of glorifying God in their ſpirits, as they profeſs: for, as out of the fulneſs of the heart the mouth ſpeaks; ſo internal devotion, if it be intenſe, will certainly diſcover it ſelf in external reverence, and adoration: for it ſeems very near an impoſſibility, very improba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, I am ſure, that any man ſhould come into the houſe of God, affected as he ought with the greatneſs, and awfulneſs, of that Majeſty he appears before, and not ſhew it in ſuch external worſhip.</p>
            <p>The moſt they have to ſay againſt is Idolatry; which is enough indeed, if they could prove it ſo; but this ſufficiently ſhews either their ignorance, or ill natures: for the proper notion of Idolatry conſiſts in a giving that honour, and religious worſhip, to any creature, which is due to God only: now I would fain know of theſe men to what creature we pay any thing of religious worſhip in any act before mention'd: ſuppoſe we proceed to a bowing at the name of Jeſus, I am confident we may prove this full as lawful, and neceſſary, as ſtanding up at the Creed, which ſome of them do allow: for the former was
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:105079:12"/>ſometimes uſed in ſome places in oppoſition to the <hi>Arrians,</hi> who denyed the Divinity of Chriſt, that by this act they might ſhew they own'd him to be God as well as man, by allowing him a fit object of divine worſhip; which they held the <hi>Arrians</hi> could not do without Idolatry, as they deny'd him to be any more than a creature: and the latter was practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by ſome to ſhew that they gave a full aſſent to all the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith, in oppoſition to thoſe, who deny'd ſome of them: now if we look barely upon the action, it is almoſt the ſame in both; if upon the reaſon, or end of it, it is wholly the ſame in each; the one owns the truth of Chriſts Divinity; the other the truth of thoſe Articles rehears'd: why then ſhould one be more Idolatry, than the other?</p>
            <p>If they ſay the former hath a bow added to it: If we ſtand up to ſhew our aſſent to the truth of the Articles of our faith; certainly reaſon will oblige us to add a bow, when we ſtand up in token of aſſent to the truth of his Divinity, who is the Author, and Finiſher of our Faith.</p>
            <p>Should they reply, that that bow alters the nature of the action, as making this an act of adoration, whilſt the other is but a bare token of aſſent.</p>
            <p>I add (to run ſo farr with them) ſuppoſe we ſhould ground it on ſome place of Scripture, and ſo make it more ſtrictly a duty: I would fain know here again to what creature do we in this give any thing of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine worſhip? I am ſure not to any Image, or the like, as the Papiſts do, and therefore cannot ſee how there ſhould be any thing of Idolatry in it.</p>
            <p>Should we do the ſame toward the Altar, yet we make this only <hi>motivum cultus,</hi> not <hi>terminativum:</hi> but becauſe the Papiſts have the ſame plea for their
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:105079:13"/>bowing to Images; take this, we do not bow toward this, as the Papiſts do toward their Images, as any repreſentation of any thing in Heaven, or Earth, or under the Earth: neither was it ever made for any ſuch intent; and therefore is not at all againſt the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Commandement: but only in regard of Gods eſpecial preſence there, which if you grant, you may as eaſily allow adoration toward this place, as reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in other places of the Church: but ſhould you doubt of this, becauſe every part of the Church hath the ſame conſecration; I referr you to the learned Mr. <hi>Mede,</hi> who about the latter end of his firſt Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumne, hath much to this purpoſe, which, I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, will give any man ſome reaſonable ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, that doth not read him with a prejudice, and reſolution not to be ſwayed by argument, and reaſon: we find that the Jews did the ſame toward their Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, and that upon the command of <hi>Hezekiah</hi> too, in the 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 32.12. which <hi>Hezekiah</hi> is recorded in <hi>chap.</hi> 29. <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. to have done that, which was right in the ſight of the Lord, according to all that <hi>David</hi> his Father had done; and therefore could be no Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>later: our Altar is the very ſame with theirs, they offer'd Sacrifice on that, we offer the Chriſtian Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice on this; the difference lyes only in the Sacrifice it ſelf, which is chang'd for the better, not for the worſe: upon which account the ſame was practis'd by the Primitive Churches; and why ſhould this be any more Idolatry in us, than in the <hi>Jews,</hi> and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians? I hope you will not make that Idolatry in <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> for which the Scripture com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends him: nor condemn thoſe Primitive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, which were generally ſo eminent for Piety, and many dyed Martyrs too.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:105079:13"/>
            <p> Should others more modeſtly ſay we are Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, they would charge us with a leſſer crime, but with as little reaſon as the other: for <hi>Aquinas</hi> in his <hi>Sum. Theol.</hi> arguing about Superſtition, comes at laſt to that 22. <hi>Quest.</hi> 93. <hi>Art.</hi> 2. which our opponents will be moſt ready to catch at, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſhew that whatever is ſuperfluous in the worſhip of God is Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious: now in this caſe he tells us a thing is ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous, <hi>ſecundum quantitatem proportionis,</hi> when ſo needleſly thruſt into the worſhip of God, that the end of this worſhip doth not require it; now the end of Divine worſhip is (according to that in my Text) <hi>that men might glorifie God in their body, and ſpirit;</hi> but what external reverence, and adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, our Church enjoyns, is not only a duty by the Law, both of God, and Nature; (as the former Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments prove) but is alſo neceſſary as it heightens, and declares our ſpiritual devotion; without which the Soul can very hardly be ſo intenſe as it ought, neither can we ſufficiently make a viſible profeſſion: therefore there can be nothing ſuperfluous, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently nothing Superſtitious in this manner of worſhip.</p>
            <p>Neither can they run from our ſubject by this to condemn Ceremonies: for he concludes a few lines after, that that is needleſs, and ſo ſuperſtitious, which is not of ſome good uſe: for our Ceremonies are of conſiderable uſe, as they are decent, and gain reverential thoughts of the worſhip of God: and adds farther, which is done, <hi>praeter Dei, &amp; Eccleſiae institutionem:</hi> whence it appears, that as God hath appointed the ſubſtance of his ſervice; ſo he hath left to the Church to appoint the external form, man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and circumſtances of it: as is evident alſo from
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105079:14"/>the Apoſtle, who commands that all things ſhould be done decently, and in order; but he not ſhewing what this decency and order is, hath left it to the diſcretion of the Church to appoint: therefore what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever lawful, and decent thing, the Church thinks fit to injoyn, becomes neceſſary; and conſequently can be neither ſuperfluous, nor Superſtitious.</p>
            <p>But others very ſtrongly hold that Superſtition is in the opinions of men about things, not in the things themſelves: as when any think it a ſin to do thoſe things, that may lawfully be done; or not do thoſe, that may be lawfully let alone: ſee the <hi>Friendly De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, part</hi> 3. <hi>page</hi> 118. whence the Author doth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably prove, that 'tis they, not we, that are Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious: others (to the ſame effect, though differing in words) hold it a placing Religion in the doing, or not doing thoſe things, that are in themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different: which likewiſe removes Superſtition from our Churches to their Conventicles; for the Church commands Ceremonies not as parts of Religion; but only as things decent, and comely, whereas they make a refuſal of ſuch things a neceſſary piece of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion it ſelf.</p>
            <p>But we are here treating of decent geſtures, reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent behaviour, and corporal adoration, which are not things indifferent, but neceſſary parts of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous worſhip, (as is before prov'd) and therefore can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſibly be brought under that notion.</p>
            <p>Should they ſay 'tis a worſhipping God after any unſeemly, or unbecoming manner: they will yet be as farr from their end, as before: for theſe geſtures, and adoration, are expreſſions, or ſigns, of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt honour, and reverence imaginable, according to the cuſtome of the place, we live in; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:105079:14"/>are the moſt becoming the greateſt Majeſty.</p>
            <p>They are daily crying Superſtition, Superſtition, among their followers; but I could never perfectly underſtand what they will have it to be: would they be pleas'd to give us a definition of it, we ſhould know the better how to handle them.</p>
            <p>Let me argue thus,</p>
            <p>If Superſtition be not in the opinions of men about things, but in the things themſelves; then it muſt be either in Ceremonies, or in theſe geſtures, and adoration.</p>
            <p>But it cannot be in our Ceremonies, for they being in themſelves indifferent, may be impos'd, which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition makes them neceſſary: as our men have abundantly proved, ſee <hi>Eccleſ. Pol. ch.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>Neither can it be in theſe geſtures, and adoration; for then they muſt either condemn all manner of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily worſhip, the higheſt act of adoration, our Church injoyns, being founded on Scripture, and reaſon, as well as the loweſt; and ſo refuſe to glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie God in their bodies by any poſitive duties, which will exclude their bodies from all poſitive happineſs, for a negative duty can receive no more than a nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive reward; and withall muſt condemn themſelves too, who ſometimes uſe ſome poſtures of reverence, as a ſitting bare at the ſinging Pſalms, and kneeling in Prayer in their private families; or, ſhould they be unwilling to do this, they muſt acquaint us with ſome more fit, and becoming modes of external wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; which they can never do; becauſe theſe we uſe (as is above hinted) are, according to cuſtome, ſigns of the greateſt reverence, which is moſt fit for the greateſt being.</p>
            <p>In a fewer words thus,</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:105079:15"/>
            <p> If this bodily worſhip be Superſtitious, they muſt either change it to better, which is impoſſible; or take away all, which is contrary to Scripture, and their own practice: for taking one part, and refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing another, is irrational, and humerſome, ſeeing the whole ſtands upon the ſame foundation of truth, and reaſon: wherefore we diſown the Brat, they have lay'd at our door, and return it back to be Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd by themſelves.</p>
            <p>But for the comfort of tender Conſciences, our Cannot doth not oblige men to bow toward the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, but leaves it <hi>ad libitum;</hi> neither do I preſs any to it, but endeavour to prove it is no Idolatry in them, that think fit to do it: wherefore I may with the leſs offence ſpeak my thoughts to be theſe, that there is nothing, that can rationally bar any from entring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the arms of our Church, and joyning with us both in body, and ſpirit to glorifie God.</p>
            <p>To wind up all:</p>
            <p>It lyes upon all ſorts of men, whether Miniſters, or people, as much as they can, to promote the glory of God, and intereſt of Religion: and</p>
            <p>Firſt for you, Fathers, and Brethren; (if I may aſſume the confidence of ſpeaking to thoſe, who are ſo much my Seniors) as we are ſet over, ſo we ſhould be both Teachers, and Leaders of the people, by Doctrine, and Example, bringing them into theſe pathes of Religious worſhip.</p>
            <p>As the Prieſts lips ſhould preſerve knowledge, ſo we ſhould inable our ſelves, not only to ſhew, but alſo to defend the lawfulneſs, and goodneſs of that Old way, in which our happy Fathers walk'd, before our late unhappy diviſions; as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſpeaks of ſome points of Philoſophy, ſo may we of ſome of Divinity:
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:105079:15"/>there is ſo great obſcurity in the things themſelves; ſo much weakneſs in our own judgements, that we may almoſt diſpair of finding out the truth, and idely fall into a <hi>Socratical</hi> dubitation: but this path of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious worſhip is plain, and eaſie, in which the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Churches all along did walk: only of late years it hath met with ſo many adverſaries, who have made it their deſign, and buſineſs, to lay ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling-blocks before the dim-ſighted people, and to bury it in the mire of frivolous objections, and nicer ſcruples; that now the generality look upon it, as on Vaults about antiquitated Monaſteries, which were made, and uſed only by the Sons of <hi>Rome;</hi> therefore we ſhould make it our buſineſs too, to remove the filth of theſe objections, and make it again plain, and paſſable: but becauſe moſt, if not all of us, are bleſt with ſuch a people, that will hate us, if we tell them the truth; we ſhould therefore prudently inſinuate theſe things by degrees, and by this innocent <hi>lenoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium,</hi> unawares ſteal their affections into all the pathes of truth: for I cannot ſee how it is conſiſtent with our duties to conceal any part of religious wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, which is neceſſary to be known, and practis'd: much leſs ſhould we tread in the dirty ſteps of thoſe worſe than Non-conforming Brethren, who to gain the affections of the giddy, and injudicious vulgar, and make their low parts ſeem tall, and reverend, diſcover a diſlike of that innocent Garment, and thoſe Rites, and Ceremonies, which they have voluntari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oblig'd themſelves to wear, and obſerve: by which means they work a kind of averſeneſs in thoſe, who were in a fair way to be brought to all the parts of divine worſhip; and confirm thoſe, who have
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:105079:16"/>already forſaken them, and our Church toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>And becauſe many are more eaſily led by example, than drawn by the ſweeteſt ſtrains of Rhetorick, or ſtrongeſt arguments in Divinity, we ſhould therefore be enſamples to others; not only pointing out, but leading our people into the pathes of duty: <hi>Cicero lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Tuſcul. Queſt.</hi> ſpeaking of ſome of the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, ſaith we may ſee, <hi>alios pecuniae cupidos, gloriae nonullos, multos libidinum ſervos, cum quorum vita mirabiliter pugnat oratio; quod quidem mihi videtur turpiſſimum:</hi> and with good reaſon too; but let it not be ſo with us: for ſad obſervation tells, that this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent age makes ſuch things as theſe a main argument, upon which they build the lawfulneſs of a ſeparation from us: our Adverſaries round about have ſo much charity as to proclaim us all either Swine, or Aſſes, that either know, or practice nothing: that by this means they may gather the more Diſciples, and the better colour their own ſeparation: which ſhould teach us (eſpecially in theſe perillous times) to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain not only from thoſe things, which are really evil; but from thoſe too, that have any appearance of it: that ſo the people having our precepts, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our good examples, may be brought both in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and ſoul, to glorifie our Father, which is in Heaven.</p>
            <p>And as We ſhould teach, both by Doctrine, and Example, ſo You ought to be followers of us, as we are of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Eſpecially thoſe, who are choſen Officers in the ſeveral Pariſhes, ſhould be carefull to walk in all the parts of religious worſhip: for the meaner ſort are
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:105079:16"/>ready to ſhelter themſelves under your wings; and think the example of thoſe, whom they ſtile the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of their Pariſh, a ſufficient authority, either in good, or evil.</p>
            <p>And know, that a ſeparation from us is farr from glorifying God: for how can that, which rends the ſeamleſs Coat of Chriſt into fractions, and diviſions, tend to his glory, or the intereſt of Religion! Whilſt one ſaith, I am of <hi>Paul,</hi> another, I am of <hi>Apollos,</hi> a third, I am of <hi>Cephas,</hi> are you not carnal?</p>
            <p>But whilſt we preſs all to Uniformity, the leaders of theſe people do make them erre: who being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd, as I may ſpeak, like the Prieſt at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> preſently fled to <hi>Samaria,</hi> and ſet up a worſhip in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to ours, and ever ſince cry, <hi>the Mount of the Lord! the Mount of the Lord!</hi> being like thoſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, which ſome fabulous ſtories tells us, have pull'd down Churches in the night, as faſt as they were built in the day; undoing in private, what we endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour in the publick: for they affright men by making a noiſe about Idolatry, though none of them are able to prove it; nor (as farr I as can hear) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er ſeriouſly endeavour'd it amongſt their people: and eſpecially ſince this laſt Act paſt againſt them, ſome of their meetings have ſounded as loud with a —<hi>Take ye joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully the ſpoyling of your Goods,</hi> as ſome of their Pulpits have done formerly with a— <hi>Curſe ye Meroz, Curſe bitterly!</hi> Wonder will hardly ſuffer me to proceed! to think that men, who make ſo great a ſhew of Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and holineſs to the people; that wrap up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in Doublets of Zeal, and write Precifian on their Brow; ſhould have the confidence, nay impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence rather, ſo miſerably to wreſt the Sacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures!
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:105079:17"/>for we know, that then the Church was Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted by the Heathens, and conſtrain'd either to ſuffer, or to part both with a good Conſcience, and the <hi>totum</hi> of Religion together: whereas we differ only about decent Ceremonies, and reverent Geſtures, which beſt become the houſe of him, who is the God of decency and order: now I wonder how any man can tell the ignorant people, that they may take as much joy, and comfort in the ſpoyling of their goods; becauſe they unjuſtly refuſe to ſatisfie authority in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing the peace of the Nation, and comply with ſome things, that are but decent ceremonies; and others, that are neceſſary parts of worſhip; whilſt they are ſuffered freely to imbrace all the Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals of Religion; as thoſe Primitive Chriſtians did, who muſt otherwiſe have parted with the whole ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Religion, and have imbrac'd Heatheniſme it ſelf! but though ſome <hi>Jehu</hi>'s drive thus furiouſly, yet I hope the moſt have more wit, and reaſon, than to talk at this rate: but as I would not have theſe men charge us with Idolatry, before they can prove it amongſt us; nor preſs the people to perſevere to the ſpoyling of their goods; and a reſiſting unto blood, with I know not what beſide, unleſs they can prove that we are all in the wrong, and themſelves only in the right: for if ſalvation may be had from the publick Ordinances, as well as from private Preaching, which none of them dare deny, I think it their prudence to ſecure their peace, and eſtates, by coming over to us: ſo neither would I have the poor people regard what is ſpoken out of a looſe, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grounded zeal, without a ſufficient foundation of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments to ſtand on: we may eaſily handle them
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:105079:17"/>with their own weapons; for I can inſtance in ſome of the chief of their party, who ſpeak a ſeparation, or any thing, that tends that way, utterly unlawfull; as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> in particular about the end of his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the Chriſtian Religion, denyes it lawfull for any man to ſeparate, though he finds he can really profit more elſewhere; which is but pretended, or ſanſied by moſt of our Separatiſts; and the reaſon he gives for it is, becauſe we ſhould preferr the good, and peace of the Church in general, above our own parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular profit: and to preſs the people to this neceſſary duty, he tells them in the ſame Paragraph, That if any do, out of ſuch an end, deny themſelves ſome preſent advantage, there is no queſtion but that God will make him amends one way, or other: what, I wonder, can be ſpoke more rational, and advantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to our cauſe than this! And yet theſe are the words of your great Father Mr. <hi>Baxter:</hi> and <hi>Vine</hi>'s on the Sacrament, denyes it lawful for any one to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from the Sacrament, much leſs from the Church, which is not ſo barr'd, and fenc'd about, as the Table of the Lord; upon any thing leſs than flat Idolatry: and gives the challenge to any man in the world to bring one place of Scripture, that doth in the leaſt favour the contrary: underſtanding thoſe places, which many wind to their own cauſe, ſuch as bee — <hi>have no fellowſhip with them, that walk diſorderly, — be ye ſeparate, and the like,</hi> of a moral, not a local conjunction: and adds further, that ſuch Principles tends to the utter overthrow of the Church; and I wiſh I may not add, of the State too, if not timely prevented.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, if our Arguments can prevail no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, let a <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Authority overſway you:
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:105079:18"/>unleſs you can prove us Idolaters, be perſwaded, as we have all but one Creator, but one Redeemer, as we agree (I hope) in all the Fundamental points of Religion, and expect to meet together in a bleſſed Eternity, to joyn with us, and walk hand in hand, in</p>
            <closer>Glorifying God both in our bodies, and our ſpirits, which are his.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:105079:18"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>SInce I Preached this Sermon, I met with an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Book (newly Publiſhed) Entituled, <hi>A Perſwaſive to Conformity,</hi> Written by way of a Letter to the <hi>Diſſenting</hi> Brethren; which I wiſh all <hi>Diſſenters</hi> would peruſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:105079:19"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Tho. Tompkins</hi> R. R<hi rend="sup">mo.</hi> in Chriſto Patri ac Domino Dom. <hi>Gilberto</hi> Divina Providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia Archi-Epiſc. <hi>Cant.</hi> a Sac. Dom.</signed> 
               <dateline>Ex Aed. <hi>Lambethani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Apr.</hi> 29. 1670.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:105079:19"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
